Washington, D.C. Plymouth Congregational Church records, 1930-1994.
Congregational Library & Archives
Washington, D.C. Plymouth Congregational Church records, 1930-1994.
RG1440
Congregational Library & Archives
2.18 Cubic Feet
(2 cartons)
The origins of the Plymouth Congregational Church start with the Union Bethel A.M.E. Church in Washington, D.C. On May 17th, 114 members of the church gathered in the home of Hannah Davis in order to create a separate organization. The members were not in favor of the church structure of Union Bethel A.M.E., particularly the power of the bishop. The first service was held a month later on June 12, 1881 with pastor William T. Peele presiding. The church has a long and storied history from this point, including in 1963 when the church opened its doors and hosted events for the March on Washington and the Poor People's Campaign. The church would continue to grow and is still active as of July 2021. This collection contains annual reports, order of worship documents, newsletters, and information on various church events such as dedications and installation services.
Plymouth Congregational Church (Washington, D.C.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library by Ophelia T. Pinkard in December 1995; 1995-02.
Historical Information
The origins of the Plymouth Congregational Church start with the Union Bethel A.M.E. Church in Washington, D.C. On May 17th, 114 members of the church gathered in the home of Hannah Davis in order to create a separate organization. The members were not in favor of the church structure of Union Bethel A.M.E., particularly the power of the bishop. The first service was held a month later on June 12, 1881 with pastor William T. Peele presiding.
The church would move around to various locations until 1887, when a new building at 17th and P street was completed. The mortgage for this building would be paid in 1897. In 1921, the Junior and Senior Endeavor Societies were formed. That same year the community raised $1500 toward a girls' dormitory located in Galangue, Western Africa (now Angola). The church would purchase a parsonage in 1924, located on Hobart Place, NW.
The church started their first newsletter, The Plymouth Monthly, in May 1942 and would continue until June 1958. The church installed memorial windows and dedicated them in May 1943. Service would continue in the original church until October 8, 1961 in favor of a new church located at 5301 North Capitol Street. That new church is still the location Plymouth Congregational Church resides in as of 2021. In 1963, the church opened its doors and hosted events for the March on Washington and the Poor People's Campaign.
The church hosted the 1979 United Church of Christ General Synod. In 1981, the church celebrated the centennial celebration which included numerous events such as a Crusteaun Feast and pageants. Ophelia T. Pinkard would join and establish the church archives in 1982. That same year, a fire would do considerable damage to the Education Building and it would take a year to fully rebuild. The church would continue to grow and is still active as of July 2021.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains annual reports, order of worship documents, newsletters, and information on various church events such as dedications and installation services.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into four series, the third of which has been further arranged into two sub-series. Records in each series and sub-series has been arranged chronologically be start date.
Series 1: Order of worship, 1930-1957, 1982-1986
Series 2: Events, 1941-1942, 1981-1994
Series 3: Communications, June 1942 - May 1994
Sub-series 1: The Plymouth Monthly, June 1942-June 1956
Sub-series 2: The Plymouth Prompter, February 1962-May 1994
Series 4: Annual reports, 1946-1994
Bibliography
Sluby, Paul E., ed. "History of Plymouth Congregational Church United Church of Christ Washington D.C.", Washington D.C., 1997.
Worship programs.; Endowment reports.; Religious literature -- Publishing; Entertainment events -- Religious aspects; Plymouth Congregational Church (Washington, D.C.)
- Order of worship, 1930 1986; 1930-1957, 1982-1986; 6 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains order of worship documents.
  - Order of worship, 1930 1957; 1930-1957 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Order of worship, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Order of worship, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Order of worship, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Order of worship, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Order of worship, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Events, 1941 1994; 1941-1942, 1981-1994; 7 Folders
  This series contains documents related to various church events, including dedications, installation services and a homecoming.
  - Dedication of Memorial Windows, 1941 1942; 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Service of Thanksgiving and Mortgage Burning, September 27, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Play about Plymouth Congregational Church, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Installation Services, 1981 1985; 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Church Stewardship Drive, 1988? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - First Conference of the Historically African-American Congregational Churches, April 18, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Homecoming 1944, 1994-05-01 1994-05-22; May 1-22, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Communications, 1942-06 1994-05; June 1942 - May 1994; 18 Folders
  This series contains communication related documents, including two newsletters, the Plymouth Monthly and the Plymouth Prompter.
  - The Plymouth Monthly, 1942-06 1956-06; June 1942 - June 1956; 9 Folders
    This sub-series contains the newsletter the Plymouth Monthly.
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1942-06 1944-02; June 1942 - February 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1944-03 1945-10; March 1944 - October 1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1945-11 1948-04; November 1945 - April 1948 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1948-05 1950-03; May 1948 - March 1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1950-04 1951-06; April 1950 - June 1951 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1951-10 1952-12; October 1951 - December 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1953-01 1954-02; January 1953 - February 1954 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1954-03 1955-06; March 1954 - June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - The Plymouth Monthly, 1955-10 1956-06; October 1955 - June 1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Survey of Church Membership, December 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Plymouth Prompter, 1962-02 1994-05; February 1962 - May 1994; 8 Folders
    This sub-series contains the newsletter the Plymouth Prompter.
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1962-02 1967-09; February 1962 - August 1967 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1967-09 1972-03; September 1967 - March 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1972-04 1974-08; April 1972 - August 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1974-09 1978-11; September 1974 - November 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1978-12 1981-02; December 1978 - February 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1981-03 1982-07; March 1981 - July 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1988-06 1993-02; June 1988 - February 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Plymouth Prompter, 1993-04 1994-05; April 1993 - May 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Annual reports, 1946 1994; 1946-1994; 16 Folders
  This series contains the churches annual reports.
  - Annual reports, 1946 1949; 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual reports, 1950 1951; 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual reports, 1953 1955; 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual reports, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual reports, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Annual reports, 1965 1971; 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual reports, 1972 1977; 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Annual reports, 1978 1980; 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Annual reports, 1981 1982; 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Annual reports, 1983 1984; 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual reports, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annual reports, 1986 1987; 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annual reports, 1988 1989; 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annual reports, 1990 1991; 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Annual reports, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annual reports, 1993 1994; 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)